<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kata Frenata</title>
    <link>http://frenata.me/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kata Frenata</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 17:17:53 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://frenata.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Speedrun: Request Headers Microservice in Go</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/speedrun-request-headers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 17:17:53 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/speedrun-request-headers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fresh-links&#34;&gt;Fresh Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://request-headers-go.herokuapp.com/&#34;&gt;Deployed App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/frenata/fcc/tree/master/request-headers/go&#34;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wherefore-art-thou-x-forwarded-for&#34;&gt;Wherefore art thou X-Forwarded-For?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the client IP can be sent several different ways, so it was necessary to check various headers. Also along these lines, none of these headers are sent when browsing locally via &lt;code&gt;heroku local&lt;/code&gt;, meaning the only way I could test that this was working properly was &amp;ldquo;in production.&amp;rdquo; Decidedly not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the full text of my function to fetch the IP address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func getIP(headers http.Header) *string {
	possibleKeys := []string{
		&amp;quot;Remote_Addr&amp;quot;,
		&amp;quot;Client-IP&amp;quot;,
		&amp;quot;X-Forwarded-For&amp;quot;,
	}

	for _, key := range possibleKeys {
		if ip := headers.Get(key); ip != &amp;quot;&amp;quot; {
			comma := strings.Index(ip, &amp;quot;,&amp;quot;)
			if comma != -1 {
				ip = ip[:comma]
			}
			return &amp;amp;ip
		}
	}

	return nil
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given a HTTP header object, this will check the various possible keys, returning the value if the header ccontains that key. There&amp;rsquo;s also a small check for a comma that will ensure only &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; address is returned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yes-i-m-pointing-at-you&#34;&gt;Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m Pointing at You&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of some note is that this function returns &lt;code&gt;*string&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;. That is, it returns a &lt;em&gt;pointer&lt;/em&gt; to a string rather than a string. This is also why &lt;code&gt;return &amp;amp;ip&lt;/code&gt; is written the way it is. It returns not the string value contained in &lt;code&gt;ip&lt;/code&gt; but the address where this value is stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is so that if the IP is not found for some reason, this function can return &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt; (aka &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;) rather than some specific string value. My Response object accordingly holds &lt;em&gt;pointers&lt;/em&gt; to strings, and when it is &lt;code&gt;Marshal&lt;/code&gt;ed into JSON a &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt; value in the IP field will be correctly returned as &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;ipaddress&amp;quot;: null&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;requirement-clarity&#34;&gt;Requirement: Clarity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely clear, from the user stories given, exactly what &amp;ldquo;operating system&amp;rdquo; data is desired. I made a choice based on the structure of the &lt;code&gt;User-Agent&lt;/code&gt; header, but it could be different. The same is true for my choice to strip out extra IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;room-for-improvement&#34;&gt;Room for Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a way to test client IP when working with a local deployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possible: display the name of a language instead of a locale string. ie, &amp;ldquo;English&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;en-US&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add other interesting headers to the JSON response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add some unit tests, by manually constructing an HTTP header and ensuring that the returned values are accurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speedrun: Timestamp Microservice in Go</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/speedrun-timestamp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 22:37:08 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/speedrun-timestamp/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-go&#34;&gt;Why Go?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I like it, that&amp;rsquo;s why! And it&amp;rsquo;s pragmatic but one-way-to-do-it spirit fits my personality. After spending months with Java for school it is an absolute joy to work with. I&amp;rsquo;ll touch on some of the more interesting things I encountered while working on the project. The details are in the source of course, which I worked hard to keep readable and annotated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://timestamp-go.herokuapp.com/&#34;&gt;Deployed App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/frenata/fcc/tree/master/timestamp/go&#34;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;heroku&#34;&gt;Heroku&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not used Heroku previously, so I spent quite a bit of time just getting started with it. Fortuanely, while not as easy to work with as &lt;a href=&#34;http://surge.sh&#34;&gt;surge.sh&lt;/a&gt; I didn&amp;rsquo;t find it too difficult to get going with. But there were a few snags. Go tooling aside, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite as simple as pointing heroku at a binary, but in the end, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t much different than that either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few different ways to signal to Heroku that the deployed app is written in Go, but I found the simplest, especially since I didn&amp;rsquo;t plan on using anything other than the standard library, was to use &lt;code&gt;gb&lt;/code&gt;. The instructions for doing so, summarized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; directory at your project root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write some &lt;code&gt;.go&lt;/code&gt; files inside &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at least one of which should compile into a binary, let&amp;rsquo;s call it &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a file called &lt;code&gt;Procfile&lt;/code&gt; in the project root that says: &lt;code&gt;web: foo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;serving-millions&#34;&gt;Serving Millions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serving http is dead simple with Go, here is the entirety of a working webserver function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func main() {
	port := os.Getenv(&amp;quot;PORT&amp;quot;)
	
	http.HandleFunc(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;, timestamp) 
	http.ListenAndServe(&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;+port, nil)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grabbing the port from the environment was another snag I ran into. You won&amp;rsquo;t know what port your particular app is being served from, so it needs to be grabbed dynamically. &lt;code&gt;timestamp&lt;/code&gt; in the above code is the name of a function that does the work of reading requests and writing responses. Originally all my logic was in this function, but I later refactored it away so that &lt;code&gt;timestamp&lt;/code&gt; is only concerned with http and any business logic is handled elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jason-and-the-argonauts&#34;&gt;Jason and the Argonauts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go also has some pleasant tools to work with JSON. I defined a concrete type to hold the data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;type TimeResponse struct {
	Unix    *string `json:&amp;quot;unix&amp;quot;`
	Natural *string `json:&amp;quot;natural&amp;quot;`
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converting a value of this type to JSON notation can be performed with &lt;code&gt;json.MarshalIndent(someResponseValue, &amp;quot;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;    &amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;json.Marshal&lt;/code&gt; would do the same thing without the extra arguments and thus no pretty printing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;time-flies-when-you-re-coding&#34;&gt;Time Flies When You&amp;rsquo;re Coding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go has a bit of unique way to represent time formats (any string representation of a certain fixed date), but I took advantage of the relative ease of defining them to extend the user story beyond the requirements, allowing a great variety of date formats to be parsed correctly. &lt;code&gt;https://timestamp-go.herokuapp.com/12/25/2017/&lt;/code&gt; was particularly fun to get working. Great apologies to the rest of the world, but I choose the American way to parse that style of date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;room-for-improvement&#34;&gt;Room for Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could this particular project be improved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instructions page is pure text, so even a little html and css would make it more pleasant to read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More time formats!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional query string to request a certain format of natural date/time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gitter-done&#34;&gt;Gitter Done&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief technical note, for myself as much as anything, since I&amp;rsquo;m holding the code for this in my overarching fcc repo, I used a git subtree to push just the relevant code to a branch. Heroku is configured to do automatic deployments from this branch. The incantation is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git subtree push --prefix timestamp/go/ origin timestamp-go
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be performed in the repo root, but will push only a specific directory &lt;code&gt;timestamp/go/&lt;/code&gt; to a specific branch &lt;code&gt;timestamp-go&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Architecture, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/android-architecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 14:07:20 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/android-architecture-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After bulding the basics of my &lt;a href=&#34;../android-architecture-1&#34;&gt;android app&lt;/a&gt;, I had a simple app that could display/edit lists of school terms. The problem? The requirements specified that the app have terms, courses associated with each term, assessments associated with each course, and notes associated with each course &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was fine, after all I was armed with all kinds of SQL database design knowledge after 3 courses at WGU, so I rapidly stubbed out java classes for each of these entities. Each relationship was a simple many-to-one relationship, so &lt;code&gt;Course&lt;/code&gt; table needed to maintain a foreign key pointing to the associated &lt;code&gt;Term&lt;/code&gt;, the &lt;code&gt;Assessment&lt;/code&gt; table needed to maintain a foreign key pointing to the associated &lt;code&gt;Course&lt;/code&gt;, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each class handled it&amp;rsquo;s own table definition rules, and my &lt;code&gt;DBHelper&lt;/code&gt; class now opened the database, then when needing to create or upgrade, called methods from each entitiy class to create each table. Add some sample data in my main activity&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;onCreate&lt;/code&gt; method, and&amp;hellip; &lt;code&gt;Exceptions: table course does not exist&lt;/code&gt;. Since the database already existed and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t incremented the verison number, rerunning my app and calling more table creation methods did nothing. My very hacky fix was to uninstall the app and then reload it onto the emulator, although I just now realized that a more sensible idea would have been to create a simple method in the &lt;code&gt;DBHelper&lt;/code&gt; to drop all the tables and delete the database, then tie this to a menu action. Lesson learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My database redefined, I turned to listing all the courses. And ran into the &lt;code&gt;ContentProvider&lt;/code&gt;, which in its &lt;code&gt;insert&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;delete&lt;/code&gt; methods was referring directly to the &lt;code&gt;Term&lt;/code&gt; class. Did I need separate providers for each table? That didn&amp;rsquo;t seem right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After chewing on the problem for a while (and sleeping on it, which always helps me), I settled on the pattern explained in &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3814005/best-practices-for-exposing-multiple-tables-using-content-providers-in-android&#34;&gt;this stackoverflow post&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize it at the time, but this style is used internally by android as well. An example, from my finished ContentProvider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@Override
public int update(
		Uri uri, 
		ContentValues values, 
		String selection, 
		String[] selectionArgs) {

	String table;

	switch (uriMatcher.match(uri)) {
		case TERMS:
			table = Term.TABLE; break;
		case COURSES:
			table = Course.TABLE; break;
		case ASSESSMENTS:
			table = Assessment.TABLE; break;
		case COURSE_NOTES:
			table = CourseNote.TABLE; break;
		case ASSESSMENT_NOTES:
			table = AssessmentNote.TABLE; break;
		default:
			table = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;; break;
	}
	return !table.isEmpty() ?
		database.update(table,
				values,
				selection,
				selectionArgs) : 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This general pattern proved hugely useful, so that the &lt;code&gt;ContentProvider&lt;/code&gt; handled most aspects of interacting with the database correctly, so long as it was given the proper URI, which are defined as public constants in the &lt;code&gt;ContentProvider&lt;/code&gt; itself. Because it was also necessary for courses to understand what term they were in and build the appropriate WHERE clause, the classes are sadly fairly coupled together, but having the &lt;code&gt;ContentProvider&lt;/code&gt; handle most aspects of DB interaction is a step in the right direction. Further refactoring could likely reduce coupling throughout the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point on, I implemented the entire database structure as specified by the requirements, absent pictures in notes, which I decided to save for another day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Architecture, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/android-architecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 21:39:47 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/android-architecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frustrated by communication issues while working on my WGU capstone/thesis, I recently turned to the only other class I have left: Mobile Application Development. I was fairly excited by this (I get to build Android apps!), but the reality of the class was somewhat intimidating. There is no objective assessment, only a performance assessment that involves building an actual app. Fine. But provided materials are&amp;hellip;minimal. No problem, I thought, since android development is so popular there should be plenty of information freely available on the web!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my original plan was to work through some of Udacity&amp;rsquo;s free material on Android, then to launch into the class project, I realized that the time left in my term was quickly running out. Not having time to learn it &amp;ldquo;the right way&amp;rdquo;, I resolved to &amp;ldquo;fake it until I made it,&amp;rdquo; passing the class, and revisiting android development proper when my time permits. My first step was to follow a tutorial to build a working app along similar lines to what I needed to eventually build. I pulled from two tutorials to get the basics rolling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lynda&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lynda.com/Android-tutorials/Building-Note-Taking-App-Android/377485-2.html&#34;&gt;Note-Taking App&lt;/a&gt; video tutorial, which was specifically linked on the WGU course page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vogella&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/AndroidSQLite/article.html&#34;&gt;Android SQLite database tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, which is just text and lots of code samples, covering a variety of ways to interact with a SQLite database in Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I primarily followed the Lynda tutorials, adjusting and learning as I went. For instance, that tutorial uses a very simple DB table with just two columns: the text of the note and the id (primary key) of the note. For even the simplest of my tables I needed to store at least 4 pieces of information: a term title, start and end dates, and the id. Thus my app quickly diverged from the tutorial, with multiple relevant fields complicating the layout files. To list data, android provides some basic list layouts, but they hold only up to two pieces of info. Since I wanted to dispaly three pieces of information, I had to build my own custom list layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept the basic class structure the same, although looking forward somewhat I seperated my &lt;code&gt;TermTable&lt;/code&gt;, representing a single SQL table, from my &lt;code&gt;SchedulerDBHelper&lt;/code&gt;, which opens/creates/upgrades the database itself, and my &lt;code&gt;SchedulerProvider&lt;/code&gt;, which is a ContentProvider to allow &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; access to the database. Early on, I also implemented a separate &lt;code&gt;Term&lt;/code&gt; class to handle bundling of the values from the &lt;code&gt;TermTable&lt;/code&gt; table, but I later merged these together into a single class called &lt;code&gt;Term&lt;/code&gt;, to handle all things related to a &amp;ldquo;term&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that point on, working through the rest of the tutorials was relatively straightforward, until I had a working app that let me display lists of terms and edit them, all backed by a SQLite database. But of course, this was only the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSSASIA: Lessons Learned</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/Lessons-Learned/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 15:05:02 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/Lessons-Learned/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What I learned from volunteering at &lt;a href=&#34;../FOSS-ASIA-2017&#34;&gt;FOSS ASIA&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say yes.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to do that thing, be upfront about that lack, ask for advice in how to do it, then say yes anyway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But don&amp;rsquo;t wait to be asked, look for a need and try to help fill it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arriving early never hurts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about yourself.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It took me a few days to nail down a &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rsquo;s who I am/what I do/what I&amp;rsquo;m interested in&amp;rdquo; routine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cards are good if you have them, but so is a well-maintained LinkedIn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask good questions about what other people are doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start conversations.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the room is full of developers, you&amp;rsquo;re probably far from the only introvert/shy person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask around about social gatherings. At least one attendee came to the speaker/team-only event just because she asked about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSS ASIA 2017</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/FOSS-ASIA-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 14:58:40 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/FOSS-ASIA-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../My-First-Conference&#34;&gt;My first conference&lt;/a&gt; had gone acceptably well, but I had resolved to &lt;strong&gt;be better&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the stars aligned and I was able to attend another conference this March, FOSSASIA 2017, I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; better. Drawing on yet another tidbit of advice (from where I know not), I decided that rather than just buying a ticket and attending the conference I would volunteer. Ideally this would force me to engage with people rather the particulars of technical talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of opportunity before the conference to assist: most notably with the actual software that would power the registration and the event scheduling, but a brutal set of obligations all mananged to collide in the weeks beforehand and I didn&amp;rsquo;t participate. Instead, I arrived in Singapore two days early, ready to attend a volunteer briefing on Thursday, the day before the conference began. I made it to the venue, struggled to the rest of the team, and sat down for a coffee to communicate on the WhatsApp chat channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much because I was there, I was grabbed to help out with the wifi deployment and provisioning, and so I soon found myself scurrying around, plugging into WiFi access points, running new ethernet cabling, and crimping connectors. As these things go, there were last minute changes and issues to overcome, but overcome them we did: myself, another out of town volunteer, and two of the primary organizers. The most important thing I did that day? (Beyond having the 568-A/B standards memorized, which really didn&amp;rsquo;t matter that much.) I said yes when asked if I could help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the next day greeting every speaker, attendee, and exhibitor that came through the doors, directing them to the appropriate places, and solving problems like missing conference badges. &amp;ldquo;Wal-mart greeter&amp;rdquo; is perhaps not anyone&amp;rsquo;s idea of a great job, but it&amp;rsquo;s actually a pretty awesome gig to quickly writeup a custom badge for a sponsor from Google, or in a pinch help diagnose WiFi connectivity issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day, I was assigned to &amp;ldquo;moderate&amp;rdquo; the exhibtors hall, so I spent the day talking to various vendors, making sure they had what they needed, running errands, and generally trying to make their lives easier. And in the meantime I had plenty of opportunity to talk to people about some amazing projects: building radio telescopes to talk to amateur sattelites, &amp;ldquo;flying&amp;rdquo; a airplane with brainwaves, building a village in China using entirely open-source designs and tools, and doing augmented-reality with HTML/CSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ambled into the conference on the third day a little bleary, having been kept up most of the night by an apparently all night party in the room next door at my hostel. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t scheduled for any tasks, so I thought I might have the chance to actually listen to some talks&amp;hellip; Well I sort of did. I was quickly grabbed and assigned to take the place of a missing volunteer to run the talks in the largest breakout room. What followed was a not-great morning of me stumbling through a job I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect, but again, I said yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between many hours of hard work, rushed meals, and achey feet were evening social events where I had the chance to chat casually with people I&amp;rsquo;d met at various other times throughout the conference or meet others I hadn&amp;rsquo;t quite connected with. Highlights from these and other social ocassions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;somehow finding myself in between an active Linux kernel developer and an active FreeBSD kernel developer discussing the relative merits of each ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an &amp;ldquo;American moment&amp;rdquo; between Jakarta-based me, a Singapore-based executive, and a Hong Kong-based developer where we shared how much we like visiting the USA but not actually living there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talking about the big project I&amp;rsquo;m working on with people actually familiar with the tech stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what &lt;a href=&#34;../Lessons-Learned&#34;&gt;did I learn&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Conference</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/My-First-Conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 14:56:34 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/My-First-Conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last August, at the first technical conference in my rebirthed career as a developer, I spent the entirety of the first day rushing about from session to session, taking notes about interesting ideas and spending most of the elaborate luncheon thinking about which talks I would listen to later that day. But while the tidbits of insight I gained were no doubt highly entertaining at the time, the only thing I can clearly recall 7 months later was a discussion of how Hollywood adapted its view of Computer Security over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since that talk and my listing of films got me watching &lt;em&gt;Tron&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Space Camp&lt;/em&gt; for the first time I can&amp;rsquo;t entirely complain, but something was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent that first night curled up with Google, trying to identify how better to engage in the later days of the conference. The clear answer shining through: people matter more than technical talks, so go talk to them! I did my best and connected with a well know personality who lived in the same city as me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But believe it or not, walking up to strangers, introducing myself, and engaging in conversation is not a strength of mine. A shocking admission from a lifelong nerd, I know. I resolved to &lt;a href=&#34;../FOSS-ASIA-2017&#34;&gt;be better&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>elastic</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/elastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 15:41:19 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/elastic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m diving into learning the Elastic stack: Logstash, Elasticsearch, Kibana. My aim is to use it to enable the local school here to extract useful information from the reams of lesson plan .docs they have laying around. Useless data right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;a bunch&lt;/em&gt; going on, and the actual process I&amp;rsquo;ll need to follow to ETL the data I do have into a usuable state isn&amp;rsquo;t entirely clear to me yet. I know I can just throw it into elastic and get full text search, but the data is semi-structured already, so I&amp;rsquo;d like to be able to extract ESLRs, times, teacher names into fields outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too much theory on a bunch of interlocking systems is confusing, so my next task is to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/guide/current/index.html&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, test some simpler use cases, then work back on my desired project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I anticipate this will be my WGU capstone, so I&amp;rsquo;ll be working up lots of documentation along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hustle</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/Hustle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:08:06 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/Hustle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After spending what seemed like the entire month of December and about half of January doing nothing but schoolwork, life is calming down. Between me and graduation are only 3 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the OCP certification test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prescribed Android app project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my capstone, essentially this is a senior thesis that will need to heavily emphasize the SDLC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have plenty of time. So much so that in addition to planning to buck for a capstone excellence award, I have time and energy to devote to other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond raising the sweet baby Reuel I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where am I allocating this excess of energy? After all, one can&amp;rsquo;t study for the OCP all day every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back to doing some FCC exercises, and hanging out in their gitter. My knowledge of JS, espespecially the advanced frameworks, is pretty sparse and although I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly want to develop React apps for a living, I figure it can only make me more well rounded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast, the little time I&amp;rsquo;ve spent learning the basics of infosec/pentesting is so much more deligtful, if less directly applicable to career advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which brings up the major way I&amp;rsquo;ve spent time, in job/interview prep of one variety or another. At a minmum I need to beat my resume into something workable, highlighting as much as possible what experince I do have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogging is sadly not yet part of my daily or weekly workflow, though perhaps it should be. I&amp;rsquo;m getting there, and hope to write more about all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the rabbit</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/the-rabbit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 11:10:31 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/the-rabbit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal is to sit and pass CompTIA&amp;rsquo;s Security+ by the end of the week. Scheduling shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem, but I&amp;rsquo;m only halfway through the material an Tuesday morning. I&amp;rsquo;ll need to prove I&amp;rsquo;m ready by the end of Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a day with elixir</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/a-day-with-elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:42:47 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/a-day-with-elixir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve pushed hard at schoolwork for the past two weeks, and a day of Rest presented itself. No new studies, no reviews, no school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polyglot that I am, the day&amp;rsquo;s learning was set aside to learn a new language: &lt;a href=&#34;//elixir-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Elixir&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve played with some functional languages previously, notably Clojure and Rust, but neither truly caught my heart. Elixir has frequently popped up in comparison to one of my current favorites, Go, which has a &lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;/em&gt; similar concurrency philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing it was simple, &lt;code&gt;pacman -S elixir&lt;/code&gt; handling everything that was needed. Before launching into exercises directly I read through the official getting started guide, then looked around for a style guide along the lines of &lt;code&gt;gofmt&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;autopep8&lt;/code&gt;. Nothing exactly right was there, but the lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://elixirkoans.io/&#34;&gt;Elixir Koans&lt;/a&gt; kept me thrumming back and forth in the guts of the language&amp;rsquo;s syntax. Setting Vim up to auto-save made this particularly pleasurable. Afterwards I &lt;a href=&#34;http://exercism.io/submissions/c1513aa32b674e7183930bd1d178e991&#34;&gt;exercised&lt;/a&gt; and tried to think/write/code in the proper paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was more or less all I had time for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language has its oddities (&lt;code&gt;|&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;?) but was sharply functional, not tied to the sluggishly starting JVM, and easy to work with. I suspect I will return to it. The Actor model of concurrency is distinctly interesting and had me imagining what it could do in the kind of heavy simulation ala Dwarf Fortress that I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>in media res</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/blog/in-media-res/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 22:06:40 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/blog/in-media-res/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than a month has passed of my second term at &lt;a href=&#34;//wgu.edu&#34;&gt;WGU&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m just about done with my enrolled classes for the 6 month term. A couple of database classes are in hand, as is CompTIA&amp;rsquo;s Network+ certification, all that remains officially is a database adminstration class on the hairier parts of SQL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I don&amp;rsquo;t plan on stopping there. The winter school break presents me with a rare opportunity&amp;ndash;the chance to schedule certification tests during the work week without having to worry about who will take care of the baby. To that end, my goal is to further finish the Security+ and Project+ certifications before 9 January. With focus, it should just be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started at WGU in March of 2016, all the GenEd credits out of the way and about 95 credits to do in order to finish a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree long delayed. 44 remain, and by early January only 33 will remain. My longterm aim is now to finish the entirety of the degree plan by the end of May, marking 15 months and 2 terms of study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/site/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/site/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The site is built with &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;//gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;—a static site generator made with Go. It uses the &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;//github.com/IvanChou/hugo-theme-vec&#34;&gt;vec&lt;/a&gt; theme. The posts are written in Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>