<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>School on Kata Frenata</title>
    <link>http://frenata.me/school/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in School on Kata Frenata</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:08:06 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://frenata.me/school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hustle</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/school/Hustle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:08:06 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/school/Hustle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After spending what seemed like the entire month of December and about half of January doing nothing but schoolwork, life is calming down. Between me and graduation are only 3 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the OCP certification test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prescribed Android app project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my capstone, essentially this is a senior thesis that will need to heavily emphasize the SDLC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have plenty of time. So much so that in addition to planning to buck for a capstone excellence award, I have time and energy to devote to other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond raising the sweet baby Reuel I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where am I allocating this excess of energy? After all, one can&amp;rsquo;t study for the OCP all day every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back to doing some FCC exercises, and hanging out in their gitter. My knowledge of JS, espespecially the advanced frameworks, is pretty sparse and although I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly want to develop React apps for a living, I figure it can only make me more well rounded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast, the little time I&amp;rsquo;ve spent learning the basics of infosec/pentesting is so much more deligtful, if less directly applicable to career advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which brings up the major way I&amp;rsquo;ve spent time, in job/interview prep of one variety or another. At a minmum I need to beat my resume into something workable, highlighting as much as possible what experince I do have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogging is sadly not yet part of my daily or weekly workflow, though perhaps it should be. I&amp;rsquo;m getting there, and hope to write more about all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the rabbit</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/school/the-rabbit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 11:10:31 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/school/the-rabbit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal is to sit and pass CompTIA&amp;rsquo;s Security+ by the end of the week. Scheduling shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem, but I&amp;rsquo;m only halfway through the material an Tuesday morning. I&amp;rsquo;ll need to prove I&amp;rsquo;m ready by the end of Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a day with elixir</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/school/a-day-with-elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:42:47 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/school/a-day-with-elixir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve pushed hard at schoolwork for the past two weeks, and a day of Rest presented itself. No new studies, no reviews, no school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polyglot that I am, the day&amp;rsquo;s learning was set aside to learn a new language: &lt;a href=&#34;//elixir-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Elixir&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve played with some functional languages previously, notably Clojure and Rust, but neither truly caught my heart. Elixir has frequently popped up in comparison to one of my current favorites, Go, which has a &lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;/em&gt; similar concurrency philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing it was simple, &lt;code&gt;pacman -S elixir&lt;/code&gt; handling everything that was needed. Before launching into exercises directly I read through the official getting started guide, then looked around for a style guide along the lines of &lt;code&gt;gofmt&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;autopep8&lt;/code&gt;. Nothing exactly right was there, but the lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://elixirkoans.io/&#34;&gt;Elixir Koans&lt;/a&gt; kept me thrumming back and forth in the guts of the language&amp;rsquo;s syntax. Setting Vim up to auto-save made this particularly pleasurable. Afterwards I &lt;a href=&#34;http://exercism.io/submissions/c1513aa32b674e7183930bd1d178e991&#34;&gt;exercised&lt;/a&gt; and tried to think/write/code in the proper paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was more or less all I had time for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language has its oddities (&lt;code&gt;|&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;?) but was sharply functional, not tied to the sluggishly starting JVM, and easy to work with. I suspect I will return to it. The Actor model of concurrency is distinctly interesting and had me imagining what it could do in the kind of heavy simulation ala Dwarf Fortress that I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>in media res</title>
      <link>http://frenata.me/school/in-media-res/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 22:06:40 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://frenata.me/school/in-media-res/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than a month has passed of my second term at &lt;a href=&#34;//wgu.edu&#34;&gt;WGU&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m just about done with my enrolled classes for the 6 month term. A couple of database classes are in hand, as is CompTIA&amp;rsquo;s Network+ certification, all that remains officially is a database adminstration class on the hairier parts of SQL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I don&amp;rsquo;t plan on stopping there. The winter school break presents me with a rare opportunity&amp;ndash;the chance to schedule certification tests during the work week without having to worry about who will take care of the baby. To that end, my goal is to further finish the Security+ and Project+ certifications before 9 January. With focus, it should just be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started at WGU in March of 2016, all the GenEd credits out of the way and about 95 credits to do in order to finish a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree long delayed. 44 remain, and by early January only 33 will remain. My longterm aim is now to finish the entirety of the degree plan by the end of May, marking 15 months and 2 terms of study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>